<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article doi="11" language="cs" publication_type="full_text"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <titles>
    <title>Publikace LaTeXových dokumentů na webu pomocí TeX4ht a GitHub Actions</title>
  </titles>
  <contributors>
    <person_name contributor_role="author" sequence="first">
      <given_name>Michal</given_name>
      <surname>Hoftich</surname>
    </person_name>
  </contributors>
  <pages>
    <first_page>11</first_page>
    <last_page>25</last_page>
  </pages>
  <additional-content>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        Článek představí sadu šablon pro nástroj TeX4ht, který slouží k převodu
        LaTeXových dokumentů do HTML. Tyto šablony výrazně usnadňují publikaci různých
        typů dokumentů na webu a přinášejí možnosti zpracování a automatizace.
      </para>
      <para>
        První šablona je určena pro převod knižních dokumentů do webové podoby.
        Umožňuje rozdělení textu do jednotlivých kapitol s automaticky generovanou
        navigací a podporou responzivního designu, takže je výsledek dobře čitelný i na
        mobilních zařízeních.
      </para>
      <para>
        Druhá šablona slouží k tvorbě staticky generovaných blogů. Každý příspěvek je
        psán jako samostatný LaTeXový dokument, který je pomocí TeX4ht převeden do
        HTML. Následně jsou tyto články zpracovány statickým generátorem webů, jako je
        například Jekyll, který se postará o sestavení celého blogu, vytvoření
        rozcestníků, archivů a další navigace.
      </para>
      <para>
        Třetí šablona je zaměřena na převod prezentací vytvořených v prostředí Beamer
        do formy tzv. handoutů – přehledových materiálů pro posluchače. Výsledkem je
        čitelný a dobře strukturovaný webový dokument vhodný pro sdílení po přednášce.
      </para>
      <para>
        Všechny šablony jsou navrženy tak, aby fungovaly v rámci GitHub Actions. To
        znamená, že dokumenty mohou být automaticky zkompilovány a publikovány online
        pokaždé, když dojde ke změně v repozitáři. 
      </para>
    </abstract>
    <title>Publishing LaTeX Documents on the Web Using TeX4ht and GitHub Actions</title>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        The article presents a set of templates for the TeX4ht tool, which serves to convert
        LaTeX documents into HTML. These templates greatly simplify the publication of various
        types of documents on the web and bring modern capabilities for processing and automation.
      </para>
      <para>
        The first template is intended for converting book-style documents into a web format.
        It allows the text to be divided into individual chapters with automatically generated
        navigation and support for responsive design, making the result easily readable even on
        mobile devices.
      </para>
      <para>
        The second template is used for creating statically generated blogs. Each post is written
        as a separate LaTeX document, which is converted to HTML using TeX4ht. Subsequently,
        these articles are processed by a static site generator such as Jekyll, which takes care
        of assembling the entire blog, creating indexes, archives, and other navigation elements.
      </para>
      <para>
        The third template focuses on converting presentations created in the Beamer environment
        into so-called handouts -- overview materials for the audience. The result is a readable
        and well-structured web document suitable for sharing after the lecture.
      </para>
      <para>
        All templates are designed to work within GitHub Actions. This means that the documents
        can be automatically compiled and published online whenever a change is made in the
        repository. This approach ensures that the web version of the document is always up to date.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </additional-content>
  <xi:include href="citations.hoftich-tex4ht.xml"/>
</article>
